foreign
it's September 29th 2023 we're here in
the active inference institute's
quarterly Roundtable number three so
this is our third
of the quarterly updates
we have guests
I'm Daniel one of the officers of the
Institute and
blue night also another officer of the
Institute
all right
we are a participatory online Institute
that is communicating learning and
practicing applied active inference you
can find us at octaveinference.institute
or the dot org address we'll be moving
things over more to the dot Institute
address though
we're inference active on Twitter or X
and here's more information this is
recorded in an archived live stream so
please provide us with feedback so we
can improve on all aspects of our work
all backgrounds and perspectives are
welcome and will follow video etiquette
for live streams
so today in this quarterly update we
will first cover some big developments
and updates at The Institute and
ecosystem scale
then go over some educational and
research updates from our edu active and
re-inference organizational units
respectively and then have some fun and
entertaining musings on where we're
going for the last months of 2023 where
we can all go in 2024 and if you're
watching live please feel free to add
any questions in the live chat and then
in the last section we'll be able to
scan over that and um
look at your questions
all right first updates from The
Institute at the organizational scale
one of the big highlights of the last
months and really of the year and of
really all of our work together with the
accomplishment of this collaborative
paper that we released in August of this
year the active inference Institute and
active inference ecosystem we had a
great team of co-authors and to give a
visual abstract and just a teaser for
those who might want to learn more about
this paper we
went through a great collaborative
process to
document and align on various aspects of
what had been
was and will be happening
and on the right side is figure one this
is an overview of the institute's
structure itself in engagement with the
ecosystem
on the left side are
a representation of our Open Source
Products and some of the functions that
they provide in the ecosystem there's a
lot more to say but blue what do you
want to comment on or what was it like
for you
it was super intense
um I think that we applied for a phase
two Grant which I think we should talk
about maybe and and in doing that phase
two pose Grant
um this was the preparation that they
kind of give you in the phase one and it
really is about
um
becoming like a big business or a big
Corporation or a big organization right
and like what it takes to really get
organized and anchor and manage a large
community of people
um which I think that was really good
for us so like we are already kind of I
don't know how much managing we do we're
a very distributed system but we do
already oversee or engage with a large
community of people and like what does
that look like when
um maybe we have conflicting factions or
um things get dropped like the ball gets
dropped in one court or another so so I
think that that really kind of brought
to light a lot of
uh the things we need to work on and
also the things that we're doing a good
job at
awesome yeah we'll come to the Grant in
a few slides but just to verbally
describe the image on the right
we have the circle
a golden ring that alludes to the cover
of the par pazulo and friston 2022
textbook
and that ring symbolizes the active
inference ecosystem and also the
boundary between the Institute as an
entity and the ecosystem as niche in The
Institute itself starting on the top of
within the ring we have several official
bodies or organs
we have the board of directors who
select officers
as well as scientific Advisory Board
which is an informal
guidance and insight Group which we'll
come to later and The Institute provides
Institute level functionality and
support for the two
organizational units which are eduactive
which is focused on educational outcomes
and reinference which is focused on
Research work the organizational units
host through facilitation other
processes different projects that are
all sorts of within on and out there in
the ecosystem and then out in the
ecosystem we have all different types of
activities and products and
organizations and players and if you're
listening to this we encourage you to
get involved if it's something that you
want to learn more about then the paper
is a great place to start
best starting place that we've made so
far and the next step is to take that
active
step and actually get involved
anything else to say on this
we should probably highlight the fact
that our Research Unit which hasn't been
formally like we've formally renamed our
Research Unit to reinference which we
haven't announced yet so I think like as
we are talking about the reinference
unit we did that kind of in the
construction of this paper and because
we were we've been edgy active and
researched and we just decided that
reinference was more fun kind of um you
know shouting out to active inference
the whole thing not just the active part
fun yeah so thanks again to all the
authors here and also people who
contributed their their insights and
just didn't want to be co-authors
all right carrying on with Institute
level updates on August 22nd of this
year we had a really amazing applied
active inference Symposium this was our
third such Symposium the first was in
2021 with Carl friston as a kind of one
person Symposium last year in the second
Symposium we highlighted Robotics and a
variety of theoretical applied work in
robotics this year we built off of the
December 2022 framing of friston at all
designing ecosystems of shared
intelligence and we wanted to put it
into play and so we
co-organized with a really great team
enacting ecosystems of shared
intelligence and here are the presenters
and discussants who joined and enacted
the symposium
and there's two intervals it was an
awesome Symposium super exciting to hear
the breadth and the depth of the work
happening in the ecosystem so for here
all I'll say is check out the program
and recordings and transcripts if you
want to learn more about that it was an
epic Symposium though and thanks again
to the co-organizer team anything you
want to hot blue
okay
as blue alluded to earlier we applied
for a phase two Grant within the NSF
program Pathways to enable open source
ecosystems so here's just two
visualizations that are provided by the
NSF to describe a little bit of what
they mean by an open source ecosystem on
the right side there's an open source
product
and then through a pathway to
sustainability
an open source ecosystem can exist which
includes here not just scientists open
source product and external user but
governance documents scientists
onboarding support external users the
product developer Community distributed
defect management development and
integration and security
and it was super fun to think about our
work in this broader sense of Open
Source Products open source doesn't only
refer to code so thinking about what is
a really rich
multimodal open source product look like
and what what is it
and
you want anything they're blue or I can
add more
yeah I just
that are
um so the paper that we wrote was kind
of the scoping document for the grant
and it's what the people do in in Phase
One
um and and in terms of Open Source I
think like we have done everything open
source uh at The Institute like all of
the things that we've done from from the
beginning of
um like our formulation until now so it
was kind of good to have that
acknowledged that like you can have an
ecosystem around education or around
um like just live stream videos or
information sharing information
management uh like we've really built up
um the active inference
Community I think I think we've been a
value-add because somebody has to kind
of organize and give meaning to
um kind of the random contributions or
not random but I think like it's helpful
in a
a field that's so new and then moves so
quickly in terms of research
developments and and everything else
yeah thanks just to give a little more
detail
the primary submitter on this grant was
the University of Washington Applied
Physics lab via co-pi Scott David at the
IRS iri as well as blue and I and
as blue mentioned it was really
fun to see who was ready for what who
wanted to throw a value into the arena
who wanted to put a comment on a Google
doc who is ready to
State their hourly
rate and scope of work and get involved
if there's pragmatic value of that kind
on the line who's ready to
work in the meanwhile and so it was just
many discussions and negotiations and as
we can smile and laugh at now a lot of
curveballs and things happening so it
was great times okay
moving on
just within the last weeks we have
submitted our form 1023 to the IRS
and so we soon expect and prefer
ourselves to be a 501c3 tax exempt
organization which means that donations
that people provide to us of which we
have received none so far
will be tax exempt
once that status and all Associated
infrastructure is ready we'll begin
philanthropic campaigning
with blue especially
we are working on policies and
procedures proactively so that we can
have comply ants ahead of time and just
stay right and relevant
it would be extremely helpful and much
appreciated if anybody was interested in
contributing their experience networks
or resources to what it could be for a
philanthropy or fundraising program at
the Institute we're open to how that
might develop and so if you see a high
leverage opportunity for what you know
or who you know or however then
some truly amazing things could happen
and if you know you know and if you know
then
help
anything you want to add on this
I do want to add that um it was really
interesting in developing like ecosystem
infrastructure in the pose Grant and in
the ecosystem paper it was really
interesting to see like what what it
takes to be a sustainable ecosystem like
to really evaluate that um at the level
of The Institute and the ecosystem and I
do think that uh I mean what makes uh
organization dissolve like people either
like you know it's like time and people
and money right it's like time and money
time and money as long as people have
time and people have money and and
interest levels so so we um have a great
like interest level as we'll talk about
I think in the coming few slides we'll
demonstrate that but but how do we get
people to keep having time to commit to
The Institute and the organization so I
think that one of the key things that we
need to do is fundraise so so like
philanthropy also but also grant writing
so these two
um things will be I think central to
keeping the Institute like being the
glue that keeps the Institute together
in the coming years so I just want to
just highlight that for anybody who
wants to come come be some glue come
provide some adhesion
um in the niche that'd be great yeah it
kind of goes without saying but it's
easy to skip everything that has
happened so far has been a purely
volunteer effort including this very
little little live stream and the last
few months have signaled and anticipated
and readied for
literally the first paid people to do
anything for the Institute which is a
big game changer and would scaffold our
time and so
that will be quite a transition point
let's continue
also at The Institute level we continue
with our volunteer program as always I
can do nothing but encourage and exhort
you to volunteer and get involved at The
Institute
being a volunteer supports your
engagement with projects and learning
groups whichever ones you're interested
it gives you repeatedly affordances
provided to get involved with active
inference and your contributions will
matter the questions you ask on a live
stream will be published by the active
inference Journal the questions that you
write in the textbook group Coda those
do become part of a shared knowledge
Niche code developments that you provide
something that makes it more accessible
or applicable those are huge in the
setting that we are and will be in so
please volunteer and encourage other
people who could be looking for
technical or philosophical education
Community mentorship all these different
things this is a great way and for those
who would like a little bit more
structured of an approach to getting
involved we continue to have the
internship program there's about 20
active interns from around the world who
are engaging with different research and
education affordances and we are up to
now five successfully completed
internships so to those who completed
it's been honor and an epic time
there's so much more I could say but
it's really exciting what interns come
in with because
we ourselves are from what we hear
people are excited to apply active
inference and to improve their own
education and understanding of what
active inference is and how they might
use it or grasp or handle it
and then to have this lightweight
internship program
that
makes a connection between the Institute
and the person gives a container and a
name and a timeline and an asynchronous
document for people's engagement whether
they're in a traditional
educational program like an
undergraduate student or a graduate
student
or probably the majority of which are
outside of a traditional educational
program and just lifelong Learners and
lifelong cool people and they just
come to
work and hone what they do so it
continues to be very inspiring and I
encourage people to
be interns and also for those who would
like to facilitate or mentor
we would like to start that discussion
about
how that might work
anything else you want to add
the active inference matchmaking service
there's so many funny ways to take that
but yeah what do you expect and prefer I
bet I meant like matching mentors and
interns and yeah that's it of course
um and then just a little summary update
across our difference
platforms and
public interfaces we see continued
growth and and activity just one
um plot this is our channel YouTube
channel growth Through Time
just kind of interesting
slow and steady wins the race but it's
also always good to see that first and
potentially second and third order
derivatives increasing
anything else you want to add
no I think like the YouTube channel has
really blown up like in the last quarter
and I think a lot of that um we just
have to shout out uh to the Chris Fields
course because the views are
astronomical in those videos it's like
really um it's really blowing up so
thanks Chris if you're watching and to
everybody who's viewing those videos and
taking those courses which the it's
truly awesome actually
yeah yeah we'll return to that but good
point and also um for people who are
interested in even social media
management video production podcast
editing Discord moderation and
governance meta governance there's a lot
of things that don't require some
technical
fluidity with the octave inference
kernel so there's a lot of ways that
people can help so don't don't let it
provide too much friction or freeze you
out if you feel like you want to be
involved but you wonder if you don't
know enough about some technical area or
philosophical framing it's totally not
required and there's a million ways that
we can work with wherever people are
um and actually that's like I was just
like that's like one of the key areas
that we've identified
um in our like ecosystem oversight it is
social media management so it's not it's
not
um you know all about the math like so
so many people come to us like I'm so
curious except I I can't do math
um and it's okay actually like can can
you do Twitter
uh because really there's a lot of
opportunities for involvement with the
Institute that aren't um math heavy
um before we head into the
organizational units here's the big
picture on which activities are
happening this website which you'll find
heartily linked from basically anywhere
you are
always summarizes the up-to-date
representation of what activities are
happening and what you can do to get
involved so I'll just go over this and
we'll talk about a few of these projects
in the coming slides
so in the space of publishing different
Medias we have the live stream project
where we organize and prepare for
different live streams following live
streams transcripts are created and
published through the active inference
Journal which through the work of Alex
Holly Dave others is always improving
and it's an exciting time for all of
these natural language processing
analyzes as well this is all being
pushed to the GitHub that allows you to
clone off the current state of the art
in all the transcripts translations
in the learning groups area we have the
part all textbook group cohorts four and
five continuing through the textbook
group fundamentals of active inference
sanjiv namjoshi's book in progress
and two courses which we'll come to
later physics is information processing
by Chris fields and constructing
cultural landscapes active inference for
the social sciences by avell at all
in the software space and activity we
continue on active block prints where we
work from both ends to make cognitive
modeling more accessible and applicable
we work from the technical capacity side
to develop the active block friends
project itself as a package utilizing
CAD CAD to apply active generative
models and we also work from the system
or domain of Interest side working with
people wherever they're at in their
analytical or programming abilities and
just starting to get the inklings of the
recipe for generative modeling together
Robotics and embodied JF continues to
develop his work with Plato robots and
societies of mind
active inference ontology
also continues maintaining and slightly
improving as well as
extending the act of inference ontology
and we have two weekly discussion
sessions one more on the educational
theme one more on the research theme but
ultimately they're both just how it goes
in the moment anything to add
all right in
eduactive our educational organizational
unit
one of the most exciting continued
activities is the active inference
textbook group
cohort 3 just within the last weeks
finished their Journey so congrats to
those who stuck it through cohort three
cohort 4 is now in chapter six recipe
for generative modeling continuing on
with the book and cohort five is
starting off there in chapter one
everyone's welcome to join
either or both of these cohorts which
are staggered so that
you can attend the same time zone and
get sampling across the book or you can
stay on one Trail at a time and switch
time zones everything's recorded
everything is collaborative in our
shared workspace it's always possible to
register and get involved all
backgrounds are totally welcomed
encouraged so if you've seen this
textbook and or you want to learn more
about what the only active inference
textbook in the play right now
says
and also connect a ton of dots and bring
in a ton of other resources and more
than the active inference textbook group
is a great place and you'll meet many
people who are also interested in
similar topics
anything else blue
it's fun
okay
um the course that began in May 2023 is
now about 5 6 completed that's physics
is information processing by Chris
Fields it's been
a journey and
can't wait for the fifth discussion
section which is tomorrow
and then the sixth lecture and
discussion and that will have
locked in
the completion of the first course at
The Institute
will be able to publish the proceedings
of the lectures and discussions as well
as the asynchronous question and answer
which Chris Fields is very graciously
answering
then we'll be able to explore
cohort or individual based learning
structures around this really first
principles and groundbreaking content
that Chris is sharing
wanna add anything on this one
just wow that's all
yeah
also in the courses space we continue on
with the constructing cultural
landscapes active inference for the
social sciences course with avell Ben
Mao Lorena and myself so Ben Mao myself
and Lorena have completed their sections
with a lecture and a discussion although
I guess Mao's discussion is coming up
we look forward to also the continued
activity in this course
as we remarked on in our
last quarterly Roundtable second one
this year
has and will see us go from zero courses
to two completed courses so both
the physics and the social sciences
which
under some understandings run the gamut
of multi-scale systems to have both of
those
at such high quality
volunteered and catalyzed by
real unique expertise
and also Broad and diverse participation
is incredible
anything you want to add blue
just that as we are starting to have
courses hosted by The Institute and
completed anybody interested in having a
course hosted by us should reach out and
anyone familiar with or interested in
accreditation is also something like
we've been thinking about how do you um
you know what what would certification
in active inference look like what are
the key like build up skills and how
could we develop a program to say
someone is certified in active inference
it's something that we've been thinking
about at the Institute scale so if you
have ideas we would love to hear about
them
um and if you have experience uh we
would love to get your input yeah
it's not covered in this round table but
the qualification certification
something that we're thinking about and
um the pedagogy and developing and
hosting courses these are all things
that we will work on
in the education space of live streams
we continue to have
exciting and unique live streams here's
just kind of a slice of Life here's the
upcoming live streams for the coming 30
days we have the round table that we're
in right now strangely looping
we have Chris fields's discussion
tomorrow
we have social sciences discussion next
week
lecture six and discussion six for
physics
active inference for the social sciences
avelle's
lecture and discussion and
a guest stream
on conviction narrative Theory
and
a new live stream paper-based series
kicking off on message passing so it's
kind of like a flavor of sometimes the
work to prepare for this live stream is
just to coordinate with a guest
and it doesn't require any kind of
expertise in their topic actually
just a curiosity in it other times we
are
operationally or logistically supporting
the course teachers and also just
showing up and then there's also work
like the dot zero preparation where for
weeks to months ahead of the live stream
we're studying through a paper
and leveraging the
questions that we have
by
asking early and asking often and
precisely or at least
legibly
that enables the questions that are
asked before the live stream by the dot
zero preparers to then actually realize
the addressing of those questions
instead of a thousand scattered
notebooks after the fact or there being
no fact in just a thousand scattered
notebooks the dot zero I'm very
passionate about because it is
a way to do the homework early and by
doing so change how things actually
happen
so if you're interested in
having
any kind of impact or learning with the
live stream organizing and preparation
process whether you have this or that
familiarity with the video and the media
and the communication side or with any
topics in and of themselves
it's super fun to invite people and have
Broad
invitations curations
and facilitations there's a lot of
exciting things that people can get
involved with so please do and other
than that it's been a true highlight of
the quarter and the year to have
all these live streams
and as mentioned earlier following each
live stream we go on to publish the
proceedings
and publish them on GitHub where they're
all versions and collaboratively edited
and also publish them to zenodo to get
the DOI and the URL
briefly from reinference
we continue work on the active inference
ontology octoblock friends
Robotics and embodied and we have
several of the Institute seed projects
related to graphical interfaces for
active inference and cognitive agent
modeling
and then there's the plethora of
individual projects that people are
working on on their own
anything you want to add on any of those
projects
no thank you okay
well
as we head into the last months of our
activity in 2020-23
and plan to have a quiet December
so really only two more months of
activity this year
and then we'll be in next year
so
as usual while scrambling to prepare for
the presentation and trying to convey
what we could and should
um I developed this small meme
so
here on the bottom is the timeline quote
timeline
we're here in September 2020 23.
soon it will be classical New Years and
will be in 2000 2024. so here's us
thinking wow
2020-24 should be really exciting
but also we remember feeling that way in
and feeling that way in 2021
but this entire concept is a nested
thought from the future
what do you think about that blue or
what are you excited about in the
past present or future
I mean like we're not we don't we don't
get don't get a treasure map right so
like that's not something that comes
with The Institute um so it's always I
think exciting to think about what the
future holds and looking back like how
we've come so far and like the leaps and
what has been like you know what has
caused exponential growth and all those
things I mean it's always just exciting
right
um so some future thoughts uh maybe
we'll be thinking about you know how we
did make those big transitions every
year and we kept making them and kept
making them and kept making them
yeah
one more specific
call to action other than the earlier
Communications to actual or plausible
participants volunteers interns we'd
like to really make a special call for
those who are interested in joining the
scientific Advisory board or
recommending or introducing somebody who
you think
could be helpful on the Sab
is an informal body we have office hours
with them and shared documents with them
it's very opt-in and flexible
other Sab members like Chris Fields went
on to
do the course and just recently Sarah
Hamburg started facilitating the morph
stream Series so it's a way to get more
involved and have a even more structured
contribution or differently structured
contribution
and it would be amazing to have the Sab
participants as Liaisons and advocates
and co-learners and co-creators
in the coming year because we select the
Sab on a yearly time scale
it would be great it's always open to
apply
however again in the coming several
weeks if we could
reach out to people
who
might have a
positive synergistic relationship with
being on the Sab
it would be very special and appreciated
for us
well
that's it for this short
round table so let's just
give any thoughts meanwhile I will
wait for anyone in the live chat who
might have questions if they write them
in the next
few minutes then we can address them or
just talk about them but other than that
what's on your mind blue or what are you
excited for
foreign
I don't know I'm excited for what's
going to come up in 2024 I think will be
a big year for us
um I'm excited to see if we get funded
or don't get funded but I think
regardless we've learned a lot about
where we are and where we're going we've
gained a lot of certainty about our
existence in the niche and about our
Niche also which is great like at any
time that you reduce uncertainty you're
able to I think you know help validate
or solidify Your Existence
um as as a organization or a human or or
whatever
um in the active inference way so I'm
excited to kind of see how that plays
out in our future uh unfolding
what about you
yeah that that reminds me of the
bookstream series that you facilitated
with Tyler and on bishan khesari's work
about
kind of
using active inference to highlight the
organizational generative model nested
generative models
and rather than talking about
uncertainty being out there in terms of
the
aspects that are not known about what's
out there
it's kind of like a glass half full
glass half an empty starting with the
certain uncertainties of the generative
model as enacted through
policy selection and so
even from the very most informal
Beginnings like the strange Loop and the
excitement was around applying active
inference to and by and with and for
active inference
in the multi-scale setting
and through the bookstream but also
through a million other
vectors
2023 has
come through
hugely on that
and yet it remains uh fledgling
and
Mason's volunteer work
as well so it's epic
um do you have any last thoughts or
we can conclude
we can conclude I think all right
thank you blue thank you everyone
hope this was a useful Roundtable and
see you next time
okay
okay nice all right
we will see you later maybe tomorrow
maybe if I can make it I'm gonna try
to
the discussion to the yeah to the
discussion oh